Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Joann Malone papers, 1963-1990 MS2368
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Joann Malone papers
Circa 1963 - Circa 1990
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
October League (M-L)
MS2368
2 Linear Feet
Lessons of the Sixties is an organization dedicated to documenting the efforts and lessons learned by local DC Metropolitan Area activists, students, organizers and those who dreamed of building a better world through new ideas, political advocacy, local organization building, and other means in the years 1960-1975. Since 2010, the Institute for Policy Studies has served as the organizational home for the Lessons of the 60s providing office space and infrastructural support. Since 2010 the project volunteers have interviewed more than 80 local activists, students, organizers and those who dreamed of building a better world through new ideas, political advocacy, local organization building, and various other means in the Washington, D.C. area in the years 1960-1975. At times during the interviews the interviewees would use personal records as examples or memory prompts. Those records were also donated to GW Special Collections and comprise a more encompassing collection of records of this time period in Washington D.C.'s history. Joann Malone deposited these papers with the project and the project donated them to GW to become part of the complete record of the history this project is preserving through its efforts. The Joann Malone portion of the Lessons of the 60s project contains documents and objects from Joann Malone, a former nun who became an activist during the Vietnam War. The documents were either owned by or collected by Joann Malone between 1963-1990. The collection contains various bound publications, news clippings, buttons and armbands.
Arrangement
The documents retain original order and are arranged thematically.
Biography
Joann Malone was a member of the Sisters of Loretto for almost twelve years, her first teaching assignment beginning in Montgomery Alabama in 1963. The Civil Rights Movement transformed her into an activist for life in efforts to end poverty, war, racism and sexism. After hearing Thich Nhat Hanh speak in 1968 about the war in Vietnam, she joined the DC-9 in an action in DC against Dow Chemical's production of napalm, nerve gas and defoliants. Her "claim to fame" is being the first nun in US history to commit five federal felonies, be convicted and face 35 years in prison. Once the DC area became a permanent home, she continued working with revolutionary groups, organizing unions at area factories and hospitals and teaching Social Studies in DC and MD public high schools for twenty-one years. She worked at IPS on a prison project, wrote for Off Our Backs, was a member of the DC Unite to Fight Back and of Earth Onion Women's Improvisational Theater.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lessons of the Sixties, February 7, 2017 (2017.005)
Scope and Contents
Lessons of the Sixties is an organization dedicated to documenting the efforts and lessons learned by local DC Metropolitan Area activists, students, organizers and those who dreamed of building a better world through new ideas, political advocacy, local organization building, and other means in the years 1960-1975. Since 2010 the Institute for Policy Studies has served as the organizational home for the Lessons of the 60s providing office space and infrastructural support. Joann Malone deposited these papers with the project and the project donated them to GW to become part of the complete record of the history this project is preserving through its efforts. This collection contains various bound publications, news clippings, buttons and armbands from and collected by Joann Malone. The material dates between 1963-1990. In addition to documents about Malone, there are publications that she has collected about communism and civil rights movements.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Related Materials
Lessons of the Sixties donated materials that are found in several GW collections. The links to the related collection's finding aids are below. Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: James G. Stockard papers finding aid Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Personal papers finding aid Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Oral history interviews finding aid To go directly to the assistance provided by the Lessons of the 60s from their website: To watch all the video interviews conducted by the Lessons of the Sixties project, go to the Lessons of the Sixties conducted interviews webpage If your focus is word searching interviews and document collections use Lessons of the Sixties keyword lists webpage.
Communism; Protest movements; October League (M-L)
- Communism, 1963-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Keywords
  Keywords provided by the donor: Communism, Soviet Union, Lenin, Marx, Stalin, Communist Party of the USA, Albania, Seattle 1919
- Play Script and Records, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Keywords provided by the donor: Stage Left, theater, music, Prairie Fire, New China, Joanne Little, Internationale in Chinese
- Iran & African Americans, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Keywords provided by the donor: Iran, Shah, Ethiopia, Fight Back, Bakke, Pan Africanist Congress, Robert Smith, Harry Haywood
- October League (1 of 2), 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Keywords provided by the donor: Call, Class Struggle, Kampuchea Mao
- October League (2 of 2), 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Women, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Keywords provided by the donor: China, Chinese women, women in the working class, Hanging Loose (poetry), Beautiful Cages, Maxine Shaw, These Days (poetry), Lee Lally, International Women's Day 1972
- Catholic Pacifists, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Keywords provided by the donor: Banner " Milwaukee 14", Resurrection Watch
- News Clippings, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Buttons, Armbands, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Keywords provided by the donor: Buttons, leftist politics, unions, presidential races, arm bands, anti-war draft board actions
- Loose Publications, 1966-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Keywords provided by the donor: Collected Works of Mao Tse-Tung in 4 volumes, little red books, children's book, Miniskirted nun, Liberation, Catholic Radical
- Loose Publications, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)